<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Maxime Dahirel</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Content by Maxime Dahirel, unless specified · Tab icon by [Gareth Monger](http://phylopic.org/image/cdc067a4-c2cc-4962-b330-2c9d02d245cb/) for [Phylopic](http://phylopic.org/) · Made using [blogdown](https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hud65e135bde620948eec5392513dd8580_19198_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dispersal ecology and evolution</title>
      <link>/project/dispersal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dispersal/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He wondered whether home was a thing that happened to a place after a while, or if it was something that you found in the end, if you simply walked and waited and willed it long enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil Gaiman, &lt;em&gt;American Gods&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dispersal (i.e. movements leading to gene flow) is one of the fundamental mechanisms shaping evolution and genetic diversity (along with selection, recombination, drift and mutation) and one of three fundamental drivers of population dynamics (along with reproduction and mortality). In the current context of widespread human-induced environmental changes, understanding dispersal is thus crucial to understand how/whether organisms will be able to cope, especially as many of these environmental changes are intrinsically spatial in nature (such as habitat fragmentation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I develop lab- and field-based experiments to understand how the interaction of various selective pressures shape the evolution of dispersal strategies and the association of dispersal with other traits in syndromes. I am also interested in unraveling the ecological and evolutionary consequences of such syndromes, especially in the context of &lt;a href=&#34;https://mdahirel.github.io/urbanecology&#34;&gt;human-induced rapid environmental changes&lt;/a&gt; and range expansions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main collaborations:&lt;/strong&gt; Armelle Ansart, Julien Pétillon, David Renault (University of Rennes 1), Solène Croci (CNRS, Rennes), Dries Bonte (Ghent University), Elodie Vercken (INRA, Sophia-Antipolis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration networks:&lt;/strong&gt; Member of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dispnet.github.io/&#34;&gt;dispNet&lt;/a&gt; research network&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban ecology</title>
      <link>/project/urban-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/urban-ecology/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#34;The unwritten rule among biologists is that, when prompted, one should answer gruffly that cities are only necessary evils where a true biologist spends as little time as possible. The real world lies outside the urban realm, in forests, dales, and fields. Where the wild things are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if I am honest I must admit I secretly like cities.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Menno Schilthuizen, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quercusbooks.co.uk/books/detail.page?isbn=9781786481092&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Darwin comes to town&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Quercus, 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the continued spatial expansion of anthropogenic environments and the intensity of human activities, the habitats of countless species and populations are now altered, destroyed or fragmented to a degree, leading to the decline or extinction of numerous taxa. Nevertheless, certain species manage to successfully exploit these evolutionarily novel conditions and are able to persist and even expand in anthropogenic environments; determining what are the characteristics that make some species or genotypes ‘winners’ and others ‘losers’ in the face of given environmental changes is a continuing task in ecology and evolutionary biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urbanisation is one of the most dramatic forms of human-induced rapid environmental changes (HIREC), and a better understanding of organisms’ adaptive or maladaptive responses may help mitigate its impacts. In addition, their standardized nature make cities great ‘natural experiments’ to study the consequences of multiple environmental changes on behaviours, and provide interesting opportunities for testing general ecological and evolutionary hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using cities in France and Belgium, I investigate how various behaviours (&lt;a href=&#34;https://mdahirel.github.io/dispersal&#34;&gt;dispersal&lt;/a&gt;, foraging behaviour, reproductive behaviour…) and life-history traits respond to urbanisation at various scales, and evaluate the consequences for population/ species persistence and interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main collaborations:&lt;/strong&gt; Dries Bonte (Ghent University), Solène Croci (CNRS, Rennes)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration networks:&lt;/strong&gt; Participant to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bio.kuleuven.be/eeb/ldm/speedy&#34;&gt;SPEEDY&lt;/a&gt; project; member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://globalurbanevolution.com/&#34;&gt;Global Urban Evolution consortium (GLUE)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also contribute to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://urbanevolution-litc.com/&#34;&gt;Life in the City: Urban Evolution blog&lt;/a&gt; (edited by Elizabeth Carlen, Lindsay Miles &amp;amp; Kristin Winchell)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
