<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Maxime Dahirel</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Content by Maxime Dahirel, unless specified · Tab icon by [Gareth Monger](http://phylopic.org/image/cdc067a4-c2cc-4962-b330-2c9d02d245cb/) for [Phylopic](http://phylopic.org/) · Made using [blogdown](https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hud65e135bde620948eec5392513dd8580_19198_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dispersal ecology and evolution</title>
      <link>/project/dispersal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dispersal/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;who-moves-why-where&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who moves? Why? Where?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He wondered whether home was a thing that happened to a place after a while, or if it was something that you found in the end, if you simply walked and waited and willed it long enough.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil Gaiman, &lt;em&gt;American Gods&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dispersal is one of the main mechanisms shaping evolution and genetic diversity (along with selection, recombination, drift and mutation) and one of three fundamental drivers of population dynamics (along with reproduction and mortality). Knowledge of dispersal is crucial to understand how/whether organisms will be able to cope, with current environmental changes, which are often spatially structured (such as habitat fragmentation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I develop lab- and field-based experiments to understand how the interaction of various selective pressures shape the evolution of dispersal strategies and the association of dispersal with other traits in syndromes. I am also interested in unraveling the ecological and evolutionary consequences of such syndromes, especially in the context of human-induced rapid environmental changes and range expansions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;dahirel_JAE2015_fig1.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main collaborations:&lt;/strong&gt; Armelle Ansart, Julien Pétillon, David Renault (University of Rennes 1), Solène Croci (CNRS, Rennes), Dries Bonte (Ghent University), Elodie Vercken (INRA, Sophia-Antipolis)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration networks:&lt;/strong&gt; Member of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dispnet.github.io/&#34;&gt;dispNet&lt;/a&gt; research network&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban ecology</title>
      <link>/project/urban-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/urban-ecology/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;living-in-the-grey-forest&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living in the grey forest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#34;The unwritten rule among biologists is that, when prompted, one should answer gruffly that cities are only necessary evils where a true biologist spends as little time as possible. The real world lies outside the urban realm, in forests, dales, and fields. Where the wild things are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if I am honest I must admit I secretly like cities.&#34;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Menno Schilthuizen, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.quercusbooks.co.uk/books/detail.page?isbn=9781786481092&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Darwin comes to town&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Quercus, 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over half of humanity now lives in cities, and this proportion, along with the surface of urban lands, is expected to rise continuously during this century. Urbanization is one of the most dramatic and complex land use changes caused by humans, combining at various scales habitat fragmentation and loss, increased temperatures as well as light, noise and chemical pollution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many species are unable to adapt: urbanization has caused numerous population declines and local species extinctions, and is a major source of biological homogenization worldwide. This is likely in turn to influence human well-being and health, through the loss or degradation of key ecosystem services in cities. Yet, some organisms persist or even thrive in cities, directly or following evolutionary changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using cities in France and Belgium, I investigate how various behaviours and life-history traits respond to urbanisation at various scales, and try to find out whether this affects population/ species persistence in cities and interactions with other species, including humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main collaborations:&lt;/strong&gt; Dries Bonte (Ghent University), Solène Croci (CNRS, Rennes)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration networks:&lt;/strong&gt; Participant to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://bio.kuleuven.be/eeb/ldm/speedy&#34;&gt;SPEEDY&lt;/a&gt; project; member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://globalurbanevolution.com/&#34;&gt;Global Urban Evolution consortium (GLUE)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also contribute to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://urbanevolution-litc.com/&#34;&gt;Life in the City: Urban Evolution blog&lt;/a&gt; (edited by Elizabeth Carlen, Lindsay Miles &amp;amp; Kristin Winchell)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
